Finding Aid for Don Binkowski collected materials, 1825-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Don Binkowski collected materials 1825-2013
Binkowski, Don, 1929-, collector.
15.6 GB online
1 oversize folders
16.5 linear feet
2011046 Aa 2; Ac
Binkowski was a district judge from Warren, Michigan who collected extensively about Democratic politics and the Polish American community in Michigan. The collection includes materials collected by Binkowski on Democratic politics, the Polish community in Michigan, the cities of Detroit, Warren, and Hamtramck, Michigan, and collected letters, postage covers, and stamps.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Judge Don Binkowski (donor no. 5501 ) and came to the library in 1974. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Don Binkowski was born October 26, 1929 in Detroit, Michigan. He received his B.A. from the University of Michigan in 1951 and his LL.B. from Wayne State University in 1956. Following graduation, he worked for the Allstate Insurance Company as a casualty examiner (1956-1957), as assistant attorney general (1957-1959), as department officer in the office of the Michigan Department of State (1959-1960), with the Wayne County Friend of Court (1960-1961), as a delegate to the Michigan Constitutional Convention (1961-1962), and as a member of the Michigan Labor Mediation Board (1962-1963).
In addition to private practice in the city of Warren, Binkowski has served on the Warren City Council, (mayor pro tem 1965-1968) and as Judge of the 37th District Court in Warren (1969-1986).
Proud of his Polish heritage, Binkowski has been both a historian and a collector of historical materials relating to the contribution of Polish-Americans.
The Don Binkowski collected materials collection has been arranged into the following series: Polish American files; Politics; Michigan History; Miscellaneous; Photographs; and Sound recordings.
The collection includes materials collected by Binkowski on Democratic politics, the Polish community in Michigan, the cities of Detroit, Warren, and Hamtramck, Michigan history in general, and collected letters, postage covers, and stamps. Digital materials include video files and an archived website. Photographs include images of strike violence, 1934-1938, at various Michigan firms; photos of Polish American public figures and organizations, also photos of political meetings and elected officials. Audio cassettes mostly contain recorded interviews with Polish American political figures.
Subjects:
Hamtramck (Mich.); Hamtramck (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Warren (Mich.); Polish Americans--Michigan.; Polish Americans--Michigan--Hamtramck.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Binkowski, Don, 1929-; Polish Americans--Michigan.; Strikes--Michigan--Detroit.; Strikes--Michigan--Flint.; Strikes--Michigan--Monroe.; American Brass Company--Strikes.; Chrysler Corporation--Strikes.; Federal Screw Works--Strikes.; Ford Motor Company--Strikes.; General Motors Corporation--Strikes.; Newton Packing Company--Strikes.; Yale & Towne Manufacturing Company--Strikes.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Polish-American Files
  The Polish American files (4.5 linear feet) includes items collected by Binkowski on Polish American organizations, Polonia and the Polish American community in Detroit, Polish politicians in Michigan, and notable members of the Polish community including Stanislaw Rys. Of note is a file on Ted Kaczynski, known as the "Unabomber," containing correspondence between Binkowski and Kaczynski. The series also includes collections on Polish churches in Detroit. Digital content (382 MB) includes a video for Stanislaw Rys's celebration of life service. Additional material on Polish politicians can be found in the Politics series.
  - Agauas, Paula 2009 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Polish Jews undated (Box 1)
  - American Polish Assistance Association 2003-2013 (Box 1)
  - American-Polish Citizens for Macomb County, Michigan undated (Box 1)
  - Archbishop Edmund C. Szoka (Detroit) 1981 (Box 1)
  - Bay City Polish Americans undated (Box 1)
  - Central Citizens Committee of Greater Detroit 1975-2010 (Box 1)
  - Chapinski, Bronislaw 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Chene Street Project (Detroit, Mich.)
    - Background information 2002-2003, 2010 (Box 1)
    - Exchange of e-mails with Marian Krzyzowski 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - Churches
    - Mother of Divine Mercy 2013 (Box 11)
    - Our Lady Queen of Heaven 1979 (Box 1)
    - Shrine of the Little Flower 1936 (Box 1)
    - St. Albertus 2002-2010 (Box 1)
    - St. Albertus 1982-2013, undated (Box 11)
      (includes photographs)
    - St. Casimir, Posen 1986 (Box 11)
    - St. John Cantius 1927, 2007 (Box 1)
    - St. Josaphat 2009-2013 (Box 1)
    - St. Joseph 2009-2010 (Box 1)
    - St. Joseph 2010-2013 (Box 11)
    - St. Louis the King (sw. Ludwika Krola) 2011 (Box 11)
    - St. Mary Church of the Immaculate Conception, Alpena 1983 (Box 11)
    - Sweetest Heart of Mary 2011-2013 (Box 11)
    - Sweetest Heart of Mary 2009-2011, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Copernicus 1973-1974 (Box 11)
  - Copernicus celebration, University of Michigan 2003 (Box 1)
  - Czolgosz, Leon 2006-2010 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Athletic Club 2010 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Poles and Polish Americans (clippings) 1926-1937 (Box 1)
  - Dziennik Polski 1904-1939, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Free Poland Magazine 1917 (Box 1)
  - Gelsavage, John 2005-2011 (Box 11)
  - Gwiazdowski, Aleksander undated (Box 1)
  - Haller, Jozef undated (Box 1)
  - History of Polish Detroit 1951-2007 (Box 1)
  - Index to Detroit newspaper articles on Polish subjects 1976, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Judicial Polish Americans 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Kaczynski, Ted 1999-2013 (Box 11)
  - Karpinski, Louis 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Kazalnica Popularna (collection of sermons) 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Ketchel, Stanley 1910 (Box 2)
  - Kolowicz, George (Box 2)
  - Koscinski, Arthur A. (judge) 1933-1950 (Box 2)
  - Kozdroj, Chesster 1943 (Box 2)
  - Krzycki, Leo (Amalgamated Clothing Workers) 1898-1949 (Box 2)
  - Kujtkowski, Adam undated (Box 2)
  - Leg's Inn 2010-2011 (Box 11)
  - Lipcznska, Waleria 2011 (Box 11)
  - Lutzeier, Paul (Funds for Polish-American Cultural Programs) 1959 (Box 2)
  - Machrowicz, Thaddeus 1916-2012 (Box 11)
  - Markowski, Benedict 1998-2011 (Box 11)
  - Matuszewska, Ewa 2007-2011 (Box 11)
  - Metro-Detroit Polonia 1976-2013 (Box 12)
  - Metro-Detroit Polonia 2002-2010, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1914-2010 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1964-2012 (Box 12)
  - Moczygemba,Leopold (Rev.) 1951 (Box 2)
  - Modelski, Izydor 2004-2011 (Box 12)
  - Mozola 1931-2002 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Polish Americans 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Nowak, Stanislaw (Stanley) 1934-2002 (Box 2)
  - Ochylski, Ed 2000-2009 (Box 2)
  - Ochylski, Edward 2010-2013 (Box 12)
  - Orchard Lake (Box 2)
    - General 2009-2011 (Box 2)
    - Orchard Lake Archives 2008 (Box 2)
    - Orchard Lake Center for Polish and Cultural Studies, monographs and Miscellanea; printed 1969-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Orchard Lake Polish Seminary 2003-2013 (Box 12)
    - Polish American Priests Association 2010 (Box 2)
    - St. Mary's College 2002-2010, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Orlemanski, Stanislaw 1992-2005 (Box 12)
  - Ostrowski, Janusz 1934-1958 (Box 3)
  - Pisarski Family 2009-2010 (Box 3)
  - Plagens, Joseph 1917 (Box 3)
  - Poletown vs. General Motors Corporation 1981 (Box 3)
  - "Poletown Remembered," Map of Detroit's Poletown 1979, 2012 (Box 12)
  - Polish Aid Society 1894 (Box 3)
  - Polish-American and Polish Publications 1970-1978 (Box 3)
  - Polish American Congress 1975-2013 (Box 3)
  - Polish American Historical Association Newsletter 2011 (Box 12)
  - Polish Americans Index 1995-2002 (Box 3)
  - Polish American Organizations 1933-2008 (Box 3)
  - Polish American Organizations, circa 1940s-2010s (Box 12)
  - Polish American Polar Bears 1999-2010 (Box 3)
  - Polish Congress 1934-2001 (Box 3)
  - Polish Experience in Detroit exhibit 2005-2007 (Box 3)
  - Polish Falcons of America undated (Box 3)
  - Polish Genealogical Society 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Polish history research 1959-1977 (Box 3)
  - Polish Home Army Veterans of Metropolitan Detroit 1998-2009 (Box 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, (40th Anniversary) 1933 (Box 3)
  - Polish National Catholic Church undated (Box 3)
  - Polish Recreational Parks undated (Box 3)
  - Polish Roman Catholic Union of America (PRCUA) 2013 (Box 12)
  - Polski Uniwersytet Ludowy (The Polish People's University) 1939-2010 (Box 3)
  - Polish Women's Alliance of America 1938-1947 (Box 3)
  - Posters 1966 undated (Box 3)
    (in oversized folder)
  - Quo Vadis American Polonia conference 2002 (Box 3)
  - Rys, Stanislaw
    - Biography 2009 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 2003-2010 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence in Polish 1995-2008, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Gliding materials 1949-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - "In the Land of Cain," 2001 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
      - 1981-2009 (Box 12)
      - Celebration of Life Service 2009, .MP4 file) (Box 12)
    - Personal 1948-2006 (Box 3)
    - "Pinnacle of Chivalry," undated (Box 3)
  - Special Events, circa 1925-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Stowarzyszenia Weteranów Armii Polskiej w Ameryce (Polish Army Veterans Association of America) 1966 (Box 3)
  - Wesolowski family 1975-2010 (Box 3)
  - West Side Detroit Polish American Historical Society 2006 (Box 3)
  - Wilkowski family 1995-2010 (Box 3)
  - Witkowski, Wallace 2004-2010 (Box 3)
  - Wojsowski, Antoni undated (Box 4)
  - Wojtowicz, Harriet 1932-1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (include photographs and cassette tape)
  - Wytrwal, Joseph 1998-2011 (Box 12)
  - Young Polonian Professionals Association of Michigan 2011 (Box 12)
  - Ziemba, Walter 1971-2009 (Box 4)
  - Zuk, Mary undated (Box 4)
- Politics
  The Politics series (2.5 linear feet) includes items collected by Binkowski on Michigan politics and politicians. A substantial portion of this series is devoted to Polish politicians including Thaddeus Machrowicz, John Sosnowski (member of U.S. Congress), and Anthony Wilkowski. Items include political advertisements and press clippings. Photographs are scattered throughout this series as indicated. Digital content (6.2 GB) includes video of a 1984 Democratic Party dinner honoring Ralph Liberato. Related materials can be found in the Polish American files.
  - Albosta, Donald (clippings) 1978-1984 (Box 4)
  - Bonior, David (member of US Congress) 1978-1999 (Box 4)
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew 1977-1981 (Box 4)
  - "Citizens' Commission to Improve Michigan Courts," 1986 (Box 4)
  - Congressional Members 1928-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Constitutional Convention Campaign 2010, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
  - Derezinski, Anthony A. (Democratic Party primary candidate for U.S. Senate, 1978) 1974-1977 (Box 4)
  - Detroit Politicians 1930-1986 (Box 4)
  - Dingell, John D., Sr. 1932-2000 (Box 4)
  - Dingell, John D., Jr. 1949-2011, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Election results (clippings) circa 1962 (Box 4)
  - Executive officials 1951-1989 (Box 4)
    (include photographs)
  - Judges 1936-1988 (Box 4)
  - Legislative 1924-1988 (advertisements and biographies) (Box 4)
  - Lesinski, John, Sr. (member of US Congress) 1932-1944 (Box 4)
  - Lesinski, John, Jr. (member of US Congress) undated (Box 4)
  - Lesinski, T. John (Michigan lieutenant governor) 1953-1973 (Box 4)
    (include group photographs)
  - Liberato, Ralph 1984, .MP4 and .ZIP file
  - Machrowicz, Thaddeus 1950-1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan Political History Society 2006-2008 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Politics (clippings and flyers) 2009-2010, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1940-1972 (Box 5)
  - National Campaigns 1954-1992 (Box 5)
  - Nedzi, Lucien (member of Congress) 1961-1987 (Box 5)
  - Nowicki, Leo 1938-1983 (Box 5)
  - Outstate 1910-1991 (Box 5)
  - Polish-American Officials in Michigan 1948-1961 (Box 5)
  - Polish-American Politics 1936-1994, undated (Box 12)
  - Polish-American Politics 1961-2006 (Box 5)
  - Political campaigns
    - Buttons 1980-1992, undated (Box 12)
    - General 1961-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1904 election, 1904 (Box 5)
    - 1916 election with anti-pole editorial cartoons, 1916, photocopies (Box 5)
    - 1935 election, 1935-1938 (Box 5)
    - 1960 Election, 1960, 2012 (Box 12)
    - 1962 campaign (Polish political ads) (Box 5)
  - Political endorsements (requests for) 1957-1984 (Box 5)
  - Presidents and presidential candidates 1919-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
    (many photographs)
  - Raczkowski, Andrzej 2010 (Box 5)
  - Ravitz, Justin 2006-2011 (Box 12)
  - Robb, Dean 2004-2011 (Box 12)
  - Romney, George 1962-1992 (Box 5)
  - Romney, Mitt 2007-2010 (Box 5)
  - Sadowski, George, 1934-1983) (Box 6)
  - Smith Oldtimers 1933-2003 (Box 6)
  - Sosnowski, John (member of Congress) 1925-1953, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Switalski, Michael 2009-2010 (Box 6)
  - Tenerowicz, Rudolph G. 1936-1941 (Box 6)
  - Wilkowski, Anthony 1935-2001, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Young Democrats Club of Michigan 1957 (Box 6)
- Michigan History (Box 7)
  The Michigan History series (5 linear feet) is arranged by the following subseries: Bicentennial; Detroit; Hamtramck; Warren; and Miscellaneous. Items in the series. The Bicentennial subseries consists of press clippings about Michigan's bicentennial and Polish community's involvement in it. The Detroit, Hamtramck, and Warren subseries include items related to each city, including Mlody Theater programs, "Melody Theater" scripts, and local school paraphernalia. The Miscellaneous subseries includes documents related to general Michigan history and other areas of the state. Digital content (10 GB) in this series includes an archived website on the history of Warren, a video file of a 1965 short film, "Detroit: City on the Move," narrated by mayor Jerome Cavanaugh, and a series of video files on the history of the Polish American community of Hamtramck.
  - Bicentennial
    - Polish-American articles, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Other material, 3 volumes (Box 7)
    - Other material, 2 volumes (Box 8)
  - Detroit
    - "A Condensed History of the Catholic Church in the Archdiocese of Detroit," 1983 (Box 9)
    - Bork, Rodney-"Life and Times: Growing up on the East Side of Detroit in the 1930s 40's and 50's," 2009, 2012 (Box 12)
    - Detroit -- Windsor July Festival 1958-1959 (Box 9)
    - Detroit Symphony Orchestra 1930-1946 (Box 9)
    - Malcolm X 2010-2011 (Box 12)
    - "Melody Caravan," 1935 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1939-1998 (Box 9)
        (include photocopies of drawings relating to the village of Norris, now part of Detroit)
      - 1943-2011 (Box 12)
      - "Detroit: City on the Move," 1965, .MP4 and .ZIP file
    - Strikes (clippings about) 1937 (Box 9)
    - South East Michigan Regional Ethnic Heritage Studies Center 1970-1975 (Box 9)
    - U.S.S. Morrill 1919 (Box 9)
    - Village of Norris 1877-2013, undated (Box 12)
    - Woodward Avenue Presbyterian Church 1918 (Box 9)
  - Hamtramck
    - Autograph Books, St. Florian's School 1935-1938 (Box 12)
    - Calendar 2009 (Box 9)
    - Hamtramck Accordiana undated (Folder 1)
    - Hamtramck bumper sticker undated (Box 9)
    - "Hamtramck and Detroit Poletown's Greatest Basketball Teams, Players and Records, 1930-1980" 1980 (Box 12)
    - Hamtramck Philharmonic Orchestra 1932, 1954 (Box 9)
    - King, Donald-"Arrivederci, Hurley--Halo, Hamtramck," 1992 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous 1931-2013, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Politics in 1934 (Box 9)
      (include photographs, additional material in oversized folder)
    - Jews in Hamtramck undated (Box 9)
    - "Julia's Prayer: Recollections of Hamtramck, MI: A Polish-American Community," undated, .ZIP file
    - Miscellaneous 1825-2010, 2 folders (Box 9)
      (includes photographs; additional material in oversized folder)
    - Mlody Teatr
      - Program 1949 (Box 9)
      - Radio transcripts 1948 (Box 9)
    - Our Lady Queen of Apostles diploma 1935 (Folder 1)
    - Schools 1939-1947, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Slovak Evangelical Union ribbon 1917 (Box 9)
    - Yeman's Hall 1934 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Bob-lo Island 1980 (Box 9)
    - City of Center Line Golden Jubilee 1986 (Box 9)
    - "Communism Comes to Farmington: The Workers Camp," 1993 (Box 9)
    - "Dictionary of Michigan Place Names," 1967 (Box 9)
    - Granger/D. Bethune Duffield 1915 undated (Box 13)
    - Historical Reprints 1888-1935, undated (Box 13)
      (Location subjects include Bellevue, Crystal Falls, Desmond, Eagle River, Gwinn, Ishpeming, Menominee Range, Wexford County, and Willow Run)
    - Michigan Historical Center 1994 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Labor History Society 1984-2008 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Minute Men 1960-2012 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous 1880-1991, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Peninsular Philatelist 2012-2013 (Box 13)
    - Press clippings 1932-1985, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Southeastern Michigan Indians 1992 (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan undated (Box 10)
    - Wayne County 1906-1982 (Box 10)
    - White, Alan-"A Brief History of Michigan, Great Lakes Transportation, Mackinac Straits Area, Bois Blanc Island, and U.S. Postal Service," 2009 (Box 13)
  - Warren
    - City Council Minutes 1873-1976 (Box 10)
    - History of Warren and Center Line (archived website) 2013, .ZIP file
    - Macomb County home rule elections 2009-2010, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Macomb Land Titles undated (Box 10)
    - Macomb Politicians 1964-1987 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous 1894-2013, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Neil, Gerald (Box 10)
      - "Diary of a Politician: My Warren Years," 1983 (Box 10)
      - "History of Warren, Michigan: 1937-1965" (Box 10)
      - "History of Warren, Michigan: 1837-1991" (Box 10)
    - Personal Protection Handbook 1972 (Box 10)
    - Press Clippings 1957-2010 (Box 10)
    - St. Dorothy's Church 1988 (Box 13)
    - Village Area Study 1968 (Box 10)
    - Warren Historical and Genealogical Society 1985-2010 (Box 10)
    - Warren Historical Commission Guest Book 1973-1987 (Box 10)
    - Warren Tank Plant 1973-1997 (Box 10)
    - "Wildcat Dodge Truck: June 1974" pamphlet 1974 (Box 10)
    - Y.M.C.A. 1966 (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series (0.2 linear feet) includes files on notable personages and other areas of Binkowski's collecting activities, including matchbook covers.
  - Byzantine/Slovak Catholics 2007-2011 (Box 13)
  - Fisher, Eugene 2005 (Box 10)
  - Garbarini, Ann Hunter Morgan 1943-1992, undated (Box 13)
  - Joy, Richard 1938-2010 (Box 10)
  - Lutzeier, Paul 1970-2013 (Box 10)
  - Matchbook Covers undated (Box 13)
  - Musical Scores-"I Want to Go Back to Michigan (Down on the Farm)" and "The Little Ford Rambled Right Along," 1914 (Folder 1)
  - Okrent, Dan 2006-2009 (Box 10)
  - Stanley, John Mix 1971 (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan (Box 13)
    - Chicago House 2011 (Box 13)
    - Polonia Club 2010-2011 (Box 13)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.5 linear feet) includes images related to Michigan automotive strikes in 1937-1938, Michigan Polish groups, and Michigan politicians.
  - American Slav Congress Rally 1943 (Box 13)
  - Bands, circa 1930s (Box 13)
    (see also oversize folder)
  - Crew of USS Morrill 1923 (Folder 1)
  - Dingell, John (Box 13)
  - Hamtramck Bar Association (Box 13)
  - Hamtramck Realtors Association member gathering, circa 1920s (Box 13)
  - Hamtramck wedding undated (Box 13)
  - Krzycki, Leo (Box 13)
  - Liberace at Fisher Theater (Detroit) 1965 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, circa late 1800s-1982, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Polish American Labor Council 1944 (Box 13)
  - Rys, Stanislaw (Box 13)
  - Rosie the Riveter Celebration 2010 (Box 13)
  - Strikes, 4 folders
    - American Brass 1938 (Box 13)
    - Chrysler (Box 13)
    - Federal Screw Works 1938 (Box 13)
    - Ford 1934, 1937 (Box 13)
    - General Motors 1937 (Box 13)
    - Newton Packing 1937 (Box 13)
    - Yale and Towne 1937 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Warren, MI (Box 13)
  - Wojsowski, Antoni (Box 13)
  - Zjazd Zw. Soc Polskich 1917 (Box 13)
- Postage
  The Postage series (2 linear feet) includes letters, covers, stamps, and postmarks relating to Detroit, Michigan, Polish, and Polish American history. Among the letters is one written in 1886 by University of Michigan Law School student Frank Malvern Mather to his parents in Ohio.
  - Letters 1837-1913 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous, late 1800s-circa 2006, 5 folders (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous, late 1800s-circa 2006, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - United Nations Postage Issues 1961-1981 (Box 15)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound Recordings series (2 linear feet) includes many audio cassettes, mostly of interviews with Polish American political figures.
  - Audio Cassettes 1972-1994, undated, 59 audiocassettes (Box 16)
    (mostly interviews with Polish American political figures)
  - Audio Cassettes 1970-1999, undated, 44 audiocassettes (Box 17)
Related Material
Additional material related to Binkowski's personal life and political career can be found in another collection titled, "Don Binkowski papers."